A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Confederate Disability Records, 1867-1887
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Confederate Disability Records, 1867-1887
The Library of Virginia
APA 112, APA 183, APA 184, APA 185, APA 186, APA 187, APA 188
30 cu. ft. (30 boxes)
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts (1776-1928)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
These materials are available on microfilm and should be served instead of the originals:
Series II: Applications, 1882-1887 (APA 185). Use Misc. Reel __
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Auditor of Public Accounts in 1913.
Biographical Information
On 29 January 1867 the General Assembly passed an act providing artificial limbs for former Confederate soldiers. This act established a board (Board of Commissioners on Artificial Limbs) consisting of the Governor, the Auditor of Public Accounts, and Dr. F. B. Watkins, to furnish applicants with artificial limbs. The applicants submitted orders from county courts verifying citizenship and loss of limb in the Civil War. Money for the artificial limbs was paid out of the treasury on order of the Auditor of Public Accounts. Between 1867 and 1894 a succession of laws were passed to provide money for artificial limbs. Additionally, beginning in 1882 and continuing until 1894, the General Assembly authorized the payment of commutations (a financial settlement in lieu of an artificial limb) to veterans who had lost a limb but could not wear a prosthesis. Through the years the General Assembly also enacted legislation allowing the money due to qualified soldiers be made available to their widows or surviving children. The board ceased operations sometime after the last funding act was passed on 8 March 1894.
Additionally, the Virginia General Assembly passed Confederate pension acts in 1888, 1900, and 1902, and a series of supplementary acts between 1903 and 1934. The act of 1888 provided pensions to Confederate soldiers, sailors, and marines disabled in action and to the widows of those killed in action. Subsequent acts broadened the coverage to include all veterans, their widows and their unmarried or widowed daughters. The acts required that applicants be residents of Virginia. The records have been indexed and are available online (Confederate Pension Rolls, Veterans and Widows).
Scope and Content
Records, 1867-1887, including applications, certificates, correspondence, court oaths and testimonies, orders, postcards, receipts, and registers detailing Virginia Confederate soldiers' efforts to obtain money and artificial limbs from the Auditor of Public Accounts.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically and then chronologically into seven series. This collection consists of several Auditor of Public Accounts (APA) accessions that while identified separately, all pertain to the same collection of records. Since the specific APA accessions had been used and referenced over the years it was decided that while each distinct APA accession number would be maintained separately, one finding aid could describe the entire collection. Therefore each series references it's specific APA accession number and each individual APA catalog record was maintained but all are linked to this one finding aid.
Series I: Applications and receipts, 1867-1878 (APA 112)
Series II: Applications and receipts, 1882-1887 (APA 185)
Series III: Register, 1876-1880 (APA 183)
Series IV: Register, 1882 (APA 184)
Series V: Register, 1882-1887 (APA 186)
Series VI: Register, 1884-1887 (APA 187)
Series VII: Register, 1887-1888 (APA 188)
Contents List
- Series I: Applications and receipts, 1867-1878 (APA 112)., Extent: 5 boxes. (Box 1-5)
  The Applications and receipts records, 1867-1878, are arranged in five boxes, with miscellaneous materials arranged to the rear. Included are applications, certificates, correspondence, court oaths and testimonies, orders, postcards, and receipts detailing Virginia Confederate soldiers' efforts to obtain money and artificial limbs from the Board of Commissioners on Artificial Limbs. The records are arranged alphabetically by soldier's last name and each soldier's folder often includes a variety of records.
  The applications were official forms that included information on which limb was amputated; whether it was in the field or hospital; the length of time between the injury and amputation; the nature of the operation whether flap or circular; present condition of the stump if it was healed or not; name of applicant and address; and name of company and regiment; and date, battle, or place where the wound was received. Similarly, the court oaths and testimonies included the name of the soldier, address, name of regiment, the nature of the injury, where the injury was received, and stating whether or not he had received a limb in the past. Sometimes a fellow soldier or commander also came forth to testify to the soldiers injury and service.
  Also included are orders from the Board on Artificial Limbs instructing Dr. D. Bly to furnish the soldier with an artificial limb, whether an arm or leg, and certifying that the limb was given and fitted. Included are letters asking if a soldier would be eligible for a limb and often include more detailed descriptions of the injury and how it was affecting the soldier's life. Sometimes the letters were written by attorneys or other third parties who helped the soldiers complete their paperwork and receive a limb or money. Included are notes from doctors certifying that they had examined the soldier, stating their disability, and testifying to their inability to work due to the disability. Also included are receipts for money paid from the Auditor of Public Accounts to soldiers for their wounds.
  Alphabetically by soldier's last name.
  - Abrahams - Austin, 1867-1877. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bagby - Bishop, 1867-1877. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Blair - Bloxton, 1867-1877. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board - Bowlin, 1867-1877. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Branch - Byrd, 1867-1877. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cabell - Clatterbuck, 1867-1877. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Coe - Cox, 1867-1877. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Crawford - Cutterton, 1867-1877. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dalton - Day, 1867-1877. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Dean - Duval, 1867-1877. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Earheart - Everson, 1867-1877. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fadley - Fureman, 1867-1877. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gaines - Gorman, 1867-1877. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Graham - Grubbs, 1867-1878. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hagerman - Hays, 1867-1877. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Header - Hinton, 1867-1877. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hogwood - Hylton, 1867-1877. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Irvine - Judson, 1867-1877. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Keeling - Kissinger, 1867-1877. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Lacy - Lawson, 1867-1877. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Leathers - Lyell, 1867-1877. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - McCabe - McVey, 1867-1877. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Macon - Martin, 1867-1877. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mason - Melton, 1867-1877. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miles - Miller, 1867-1877. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Montgomery - Murphy, 1867-1877. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Nash - Nunn, 1867-1877. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Oliver - Owen, 1867-1877. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Page - Pettus, 1867-1877. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Phillips - Pugh, 1867-1877. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Ragland - Ring, 1867-1877. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Roberson - Ryan, 1867-1877. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - St. Clair - Skinker, 1867-1877. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Smith - Spotts, 1867-1877. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Stanley - Sutphin, 1867-1877. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Taliaferro - Terry, 1867-1877. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Thomas - Thurston, 1867-1877. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Tibbs - Turpin, 1867-1877. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Vanfossen - Vaughn, 1867-1877. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Walker - Wayland, 1867-1877. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Webb - Westwood, 1867-1877. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Wheeler - Whitlock, 1867-1877. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Wigginton - Wilks, 1867-1877. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Williams - Wise, 1867-1877. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Womack - Wyrick, 1867-1877. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Young - Yowell, 1867-1877. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1867-1877. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series II: Applications and receipts, 1882-1887 (APA 185)., Extent: 24 boxes (24 cu. ft.). (Box 6-29)
  The Applications and receipts records, 1882-1887, are arranged by year and then alphabetically by soldiers last names in twenty-five boxes. Included are applications, certificates, correspondence, court oaths and testimonies, orders, postcards, power of attorneys, and receipts detailing Virginia Confederate soldiers' efforts to obtain money for their disabilities received during the Civil War. Included are court testimonies and certificates from the soldiers stating their names, unit they served, battle and date of injury, and type of injury. Also often doctors stated they find the person permanently disabled and explained the wounds. Included are form letters from the APA to the soldier enclosing a check for an amount due them for commutation under the act of the General Assembly.
  Arranged chronologically and then alphabetically by soldiers' last name.
  - 1882
    - Abbott - Curtis. (Box 6)
    - Dalton - Heslip. (Box 7)
    - . (Box 8)
    - . (Box 9)
    - . (Box 10)
    - Abbott - Collins. (Box 11)
    - Combs - Gwynn. (Box 12)
    - . (Box 13)
    - . (Box 14)
    - Addison - Byrd. (Box 15)
    - Cabaniss - Cyrus. (Box 16)
    - . (Box 17)
    - . (Box 18)
    - . (Box 19)
    - . (Box 20)
    - . (Box 21)
    - . (Box 22)
    - . (Box 23)
    - . (Box 24)
    - . (Box 25)
    - . (Box 26)
    - Abbott - Durham. (Box 27)
    - . (Box 28)
    - . (Box 29)
- Series III: Register, 1876-1880 (APA 183)., Extent: 1 volume. (Box 30)
  Register, 1876-1880, listing Virginia Confederate soldiers who received either an artificial limb or payment for their disabilities from the Auditor of Public Accounts. There are two lists of disabled soldiers established by type of compensation: artificial limb or payment. The first list is arranged alphabetically by locality and includes the soldier's name, regiment, limb lost, and battle. The second list is alphabetical by surname and includes the soldier's name, place of residence, nature of disability, and date paid. There are several alphabetical lists throughout the volume so it is necessary for researchers to search the entire volume. A few loose papers are housed in a folder.
- Series IV: Register, 1882 (APA 184)., Extent: 1 volume. (Box 31)
  Register, 1882, listing Virginia Confederate soldiers who received payment for their disabilities from the Auditor of Public Accounts. The register is arranged alphabetically by soldiers' last name and lists their residence. On each page the names on the left side of the page received $60.00 while those on the right side received $30.00. The register dates from an Act of Assembly dated 14 February 1882.
- Series V: Register, 1882-1887 (APA 186)., Extent: 1 volume. (Box 32)
  Register, 1882-1887, listing Virginia Confederate soldiers who received payment for their disabilities from the Auditor of Public Accounts. The volume is organized alphabetically by claims allowed - Class No. 1 and Class No. 2 - and then claims not allowed - Class No. 1 and Class No. 2. The volume lists the date of claim filing, name of soldiers, residence, date of payment, nature of disability, and to whom paid.
- Series VI: Register, 1884-1887 (APA 187)., Extent: 2 volumes. (Box 31)
  Registers, 1884-1887, listing Virginia Confederate soldiers who received payment for their disabilities from the Auditor of Public Accounts. There are 2 volumes: Volume 1 dating 1884-1886, and Volume 2 dating 1886-1887 (applications filed on and since 5 February 1886). The registers list the soldiers names, residence, and date of filing.
- Series VII: Register, 1887-1888 (APA 188)., Extent: 1 volume. (Box 31)
  Register, 1887-1888, listing Virginia Confederate soldiers who received payment for their disabilities from the Auditor of Public Accounts. The registers list the soldiers names, residence, date of filing, and notes if a request was returned or disallowed. The register dates from an Act of Assembly dated 23 May 1887.